A Guide to the Population Council records, Miscellaneous Files, Record Group 2, Accession 2, Series 17 FA1438
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council records, Miscellaneous Files, Record Group 2, Accession 2, Series 17
1959-1986
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council
FA1438
6.5 Cubic Feet 5 letter-size document boxes, 4 legal-size document boxes, 1 half-letter document box, and 1 standard record storage box.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Population Council was founded by John D. Rockefeller 3rd in 1952 to undertake "significant activities in the broad field of population." Its goal has been to bring about a reduction in the number of births that occur in the world. In its early years, the business of the Population Council was conducted by a Demographic Division and a Biomedical Division. Through its Demographic Division, the Council sought to document what it conceived to be an overpopulation problem threatening many areas of the world. To accomplish this purpose, the Division facilitated research on the economic, social, and psychological factors which affect the growth and decline of human population. This Council-assisted research effort was conducted not only by staff of the Demographic Division but also by other institutions and scholars, some of whom received Council grants and fellowships and some of whom received informal advice and consultation on how to design and execute studies.
The Biomedical Division, which, beginning in 1959, occupied a laboratory at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), has conducted pure and applied research on plant, animal, and human reproductive physiology and on the development, the physiological action, and the safety and effectiveness of contraceptive methods. The Council facilitated similar types of medical research by non-Council scientists at other institutions by giving grants and fellowships for such research. The Council's biomedical research and its support for research by non-Council scientists were instrumental in the development of the modern intrauterine coil and the birth control pill.
In about 1960, the scope of Population Council activities expanded. The Council began to render practical and technical aid to foreign nations. Beginning in that year, the Demographic Division, in addition to supervising research, became involved in Pakistan's family planning program, extending practical and technical aid in organizing and running a national family planning program. By 1964 the Council's Demographic Division had assisted in organizing family planning programs in South Korea, Taiwan, Thailand, Tunisia, and Turkey. In that year, the Council created the Technical Assistance Division. This division, in ensuing years, continued the assistance of the Council in the countries where it had already become involved and also helped start and run programs in India, Morocco, the Philippines, and Puerto Rico.
An underlying aim of the Council's grant programs has been to encourage the development and growth of institutions that would promote family planning programs. To this end, the Council has given grants and advice to various universities and research centers for starting and upgrading programs for demographic and biomedical training and research programs; has assisted the United Nations to set up and expand regional Demographic Training and Research Centres in Bombay, India, Santiago, Chile, and Cairo, Egypt; has worked with the Ford Foundation on family planning programs in Pakistan, India, and North Africa.
In addition to rendering technical aid and sponsoring research, the Council has undertaken several complementary public relations efforts. To reach the general populations of the United States and of foreign nations, Council officers have worked to inform the mass media about population issues and to encourage magazine articles, movies, and books dealing with population matters. Council officers and representatives have also made trips and prepared reports to convince various foreign government leaders of the importance and the desirability of promulgating family planning programs. In addition, Council officers participated in and helped organize and finance conferences for demographers and medical scientists active in population work.
The Population Council has obtained its financial support through large contributions. The Ford and Rockefeller Foundations and the Rockefeller Brothers Fund have been the principal institutional supporters of the Council. John D. Rockefeller 3rd has been the single most significant individual backer of the Council.
Arrangement
Original order is maintained, as received.
Scope and Contents
The Miscellaneous Files document a wide variety of subject matter and file types including but not limited to meeting records, lectures, receptions and events, real estate files, planning and proposal documents, field staff and trip files. There is also a small selection of Taiwan files including correspondence and reports.
- Miscellaneous Files, 1959-1986; 17
  - Experiment in International Living (EIL) - Correspondence and General Material, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Experiment in International Living (EIL) - Board of Trustees, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Experiment in International Living (EIL) - Executive Committee, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Experiment in International Living (EIL) - Finance Committee, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Population Council - Real Estate Research, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sample Brochures, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Population Council Brochure, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - China - Qian Dinner, 1983 October (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Qian Lecture - Qian Speech, George Zeidenstein Introduction, Question and Answer Session, 1983 October (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Qian Lecture - Recipients of Qian Speech, 1983 September-November (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Qian Lecture - Logistics, 1983 October (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Qian Lecture - Correspondence, 1983 September-October (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Qian Lecture - Samples, 1983 October (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Qian Lecture - List of Invitees, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - One Dag Correspondence - Vendors, 1976-1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Environetics, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - One Times Square, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Sandy Perlowin Associates, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - United Nations Population Commission Reception, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - United Nations Population Commission Reception, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Public Issues Papers, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Public Issues Papers - U.S. Immigration Policy: Foreign and Domestic Implications, 1979 May 9 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Sato Dinner Reception, 1985 September 23 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Social Security and the Population Council, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Studies in Family Planning, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Space and Location, 1973-1981 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Support Services, 1976-1981 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Research and Evaluation - Thailand - Field Staff, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Lippes Loops - Purchase Orders, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Ford Foundation-Population Council - Asia Meetings, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Hoogenboom - Trip - East and Southeast Asia, 1970 June (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Personnel and Payroll (Box 5, Folder 33)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - Personnel material
  - Legal Counsel, 1966-1975 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    Restricted - Confidential material
  - Population Council New Headquarters, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Asia Meetings, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) Medical School Program, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Woods Hole Meeting, 1976 July (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Population Policy - Law Proposals, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Action Summary Report - Council Grants, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Personnel Files, 1964-1972 (Box 6)
  - Affirmative Action, 1977-1981 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Affirmative Action, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Public Affairs Program, 1976-1981 (Box 7, Folder 43-44)
  - Real Estate, 1976-1982 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Communications Program - Ruder and Finn, 1980-1982 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Taiwan - Academia Sinica, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Taiwan - Commissioner of Health - Hsu, T. C., 1963-1966 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Taiwan - Family Planning Association of China, 1959-1966 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Taiwan - Joint Commission on Rural Reconstruction, 1959-1966 (Box 8, Folder 50-51)
  - Taiwan - Keeny, Sam - Nobel Prize, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Taiwan - Keeny, Sam - Personal, 1963-1965 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Taiwan - Keeny, Sam - Newsletter, 1963-1966 (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - Taiwan - Keeny, Sam, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - Taiwan - Joint Commission on Rural Reconstruction - AID - Financial Assistance Proposal, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - Taiwan - Joint Commission on Rural Reconstruction - Family Planning Action and Research Reports, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - Taiwan - Joint Commission on Rural Reconstruction - Liu, Paul, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - Taiwan - Joint Commission on Rural Reconstruction - Reports, 1964-1966 (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Taiwan - KAP - Reports and Studies, 1962-1965 (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - Taiwan - Keeny, Sam, 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Taiwan - National Taiwan University, 1959-1964 (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - Taiwan - Population Studies Center, 1961-1964 May (Box 9, Folder 63-64)
  - Taiwan - Population Studies Center - Audiovisual Material, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - Taiwan - Population Studies Center, 1964 July-1966 (Box 10, Folder 66)
  - Taiwan - Population Studies Center - Financial Reports, 1962-1966 (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - Taiwan - Population Studies Center - Equipment (Box 10, Folder 68)
  - Taiwan - Population Studies Center - Brown, Dr. Donald, 1962-1964 (Box 10, Folder 69)
  - Taiwan - Population Studies Center - Cernada, George P., 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 70-72)
  - Taiwan - Population Studies Center - Chow, L. P., 1961-1966 (Box 10, Folder 73-75)
  - Taiwan - Population Studies Center - Chow, L. P., 1963-1966 (Box 11, Folder 76)
  - Taiwan - Population Studies Center - Gillespie, Robert, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 77)